Guide to the Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection
1844-1899
WA Photos 402
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
25.5
(54 boxes)
This collection consists of daguerreotypes, ambrotypes, tintypes, and collodion processes primarily mounted in contemporary decorative cases, collected by Peter Palmquist to document photographers, photographic processes and presentation techniques in the United States, especially in California, and in Great Britain, circa 1844-1899.
Palmquist, Peter E.
Allen, Charles V., 1828-
Atkinson, S. J.
Beals, Albert J.
Beardsley, B. C.
Broadbent, S. (Samuel), 1810-1881
Cary, Charles H.
Clayton, James A. (James Atkins), 1831-1896
Cook, William H.
Coombs, F. (Frederick)
Daniels, A. F. (Austin Fitzerland), 1832-
Fardon, G. R.
Fetter, Harvey G.
Fitzgibbon, John H., 1816?-1882
Ford, James May, 1827-approximately 1877
Gutekunst, Frederick, 1831-1917
Hale, L.H., 1823-1885
Hamilton, Charles F., approximately 1825-
Hamilton, George D.
Harris, Theodore
Hathaway, William
Hawes, Charles E.
Hickling, J.
Higgins, Thomas J.
Johnson, George Howard, 1823-
Lenox, Isaac Shaw
Long, Enoch
Maxham, B. D. (Benjamin Dexter), 1821-1899
McIntyre, Sterling C.
Merrill, James O.
Norcross, Oliver H. P., 1824-1871
Outley, John J.
Phillips, J. A.
Pine, George W.
Plumbe, John, 1809-1857
Rehn, Isaac
Ruth, J.
Selleck, Silas Wright, approximately 1828-1885
Shaw, Seth Louis
Shew, Jacob, approximately 1826-1879
Shew, Myron, 1824-1891
Shew, William J., 1820-1903
Silver, O. B.
Spooner, John Pitcher, 1845-1917
Vance, Robert H., 1825-1876
Whitehurst, Jesse Harrison, 1819-1875
Culver & Fellows (Newport, New Hampshire)
Pine & Bells (Troy, New York)
Shaw & Johnson (San Francisco, California)
Spooner Brothers (Springfield, Massachusetts)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Peter E. Palmquist on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
PETER E. PALMQUIST (1936-2003)
A photographer, collector, and historian of photography, Peter Eric Palmquist was born on September 23, 1936, in Oakland, California. In 1944, he moved with his family to Ferndale, California, and spent the majority of his life in Humboldt County. Palmquist trained himself in photography as an adolescent, and served as a photographer in the United States Army, 1955-1959, attached to the Supreme Headquarters Allied Powers Europe in Paris. He worked briefly as a photographer for the state government of California from 1959-1961. From 1961 until his retirement in 1989, Palmquist worked as a staff photographer for Humboldt State University, Arcata, California, where he also graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in Art in 1965.
From 1971 until his death, Palmquist collected historical and contemporary photographs and information about photographers. He collected hundreds of thousands of photographic items documenting the practice and occupation of photography from its inception through the turn of the twenty-first century, with particular emphasis on early California photographers, photographers of the American West, and women photographers from around the world.
A self-trained researcher and historian of photography, Palmquist organized over a hundred exhibitions and wrote over three hundred articles and more than sixty monographs. He was a founding editor of The Daguerreian Annual; president of the National Stereoscopic Association; and founder and curator of the Women in Photography International Archive.
Palmquist died January 13, 2003, in Oakland, from a severe head injury caused by a speeding car that struck him while he was in a crosswalk with his dog.
Scope and Contents
The Peter Palmquist Cased Photographs Collection consists of daguerreotypes, ambrotypes, tintypes, and wet collodion processes mounted primarily in contemporary decorative cases, collected by Peter Palmquist of Arcata, California, during the last quarter of the twentieth century. Items in the collection document photographic processes and presentation techniques in the United States, especially in California, and in Great Britain, circa 1844-1873.
The finding aid contains 410 entries for individual items or small collections of related material. It is housed in boxes and organized into six series: Images by Identified Photographers, Identified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, Identified Places by Unidentified Photographers, Unidentified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, Cased Photograph Components, and Associated Printed Material. The detailed notes associated with individual items derive from documentation collected or attributed by Palmquist and verified whenever possible by the processing archivist. [An arbitrary numbering scheme assigned to the items by Palmquist is reflected in a concordance in the appendix.] References to specific decorative motifs on cases correspond to reference numbers in Floyd Rinhart and Marion Rinhart, American Miniature Case Art (New York: A.S. Barnes, 1969) and Clifford Krainik, Michelle Krainik, and Carl Walvoord, Union Cases, A Collector's Guide to the Art of America's First Plastics (Grantsburg, Wisconsin: Centennial Photo Service, 1988).
Series I. Images by Identified Photographers, contains 161 items spanning the dates 1844-1873, and is organized geographically into twelve subseries, including California photographers (for which there are 112 items), other states, Great Britain, and a final subseries for photographers whose location remains unidentified. Within each subseries the entries are arranged alphabetically according to the surname or corporate name of the photographer. This series also contains several examples of cased photograph components which document the work of a specific photographer.
Represented California photographers include several from San Francisco: Frederick C. Coombs, George Robinson Fardon, James May Ford, Charles F. Hamilton, Silas Wright Selleck, Shaw & Johnson (Seth Louis Shaw and George Howard Johnson), William Shew, and Robert H. Vance. Photographers representing other localities in California include James Atkins Clayton of San Jose; William H. Cook of Marysville; Thomas J. Higgins of Sacramento; George Howard Johnson of Sacramento; Oliver H. P. Norcross of Weaverville; J. Ruth of Marysville; Jacob Shew of Sacramento; O. B. Silver of Dutch Flat; and John Pitcher Spooner of Stockton.
Other localities in the United States for which there are significant numbers of images include Massachusetts, Missouri, New York, and Pennsylvania. Photographers in Massachusetts include Boston photographers Charles V. Allen, Luther Holman Hale, George D. Hamilton, and William Shew; Worcester photographers Austin F. Daniels and Benjamin D. Maxham; New Bedford photographers William Hathaway and Charles E. Hawes; and the Spooner Brothers of Springfield.
Photographers in St. Louis, Missouri, include John H. Fitzgibbon, Enoch Long, and John J. Outley. Photographers in New York include Albert J. Beals, Charles H. Cary, and Sterling C. McIntyre in New York City, J. A. Phillips of Fredonia, and Pine & Bells (George W. Pine) of Troy. Photographers in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, include Samuel Broadbent, Frederick Gutekunst, Isaac Rehn, and Myron Shew.
Identified photographers representing other states include Badgley of Centre, Alabama; Harvey G. Fetter of Peru, Iowa; Swan of Birmingham, Iowa; Theodore Harris of Louisville, Kentucky; Culver & Fellows of Newport, New Hampshire; and James O. Merrill of Brandon, Vermont.
Photographers from Great Britain include English photographers J. Hickling of either Ramsgate or Margate, and Isaac Shaw Lenox of Bristol, in addition to Scottish photographer Ritchie of Edinburgh.
Identified photographers with unidentified locations include S. J. Atkinson, B. C. Beardsley, Hamilton, John Plumbe, Jr., and Jesse Harrison Whitehurst.
Series II, Identified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, contains 26 items that span the dates 1850-1860, and is arranged alphabetically according to the surname or corporate name of the subject. Identified individuals include members of the Alviso, Perlata, and Vallejo families of Oakland, California; George Amy; C. A. Anderson; C. D. Brown; Eugene Cammerer; Edward Carl; Etta Corning; Jane Drummond; F. M. Failing; Albert Hartwell; A. S. Lid; Jennie Merriam; Selah Merrill; Jack Miller; Fred Nancki; Daniel Showalter; Ben Smith; Francis Uslar; Francis Otto Wagener; and Gertrude Wightman.
Series III, Identified Places by Unidentified Photographers, contains 16 items that span the dates 1852-1860, arranged geographically by state, and where possible by city within each state. Locations include California, Iowa, New York, and the New England region. Specific identified localities include Eureka or Trinidad, California; San Francisco, California; La Moille, Iowa; and Niagara Falls, New York. Most locations have been assigned based on attributions by Peter Palmquist.
Series IV, Unidentified Subjects by Unidentified Photographers, contains 132 items that span the dates 1840-1869, and is organized into four subseries: Single Individuals, Couples, Groups, and Objects. Items depicting Single Individuals are arranged under headings for Infants, Girls, Boys, Women, and Men. Items depicting Couples are arranged under headings for Infant and Adult, Children, Child and Adult, Women, Men, and Woman and Man. Under each heading items are arranged chronologically.
Series V. Cased Photograph Components, contains 22 items and spans the dates 1844-1869. It consists of items used in the construction of cased photographs, and is comprised primarily of cases and mats. It is organized into four subseries. The first subseries consists of cases by identified manufacturers, arranged alphabetically. The second subseries consists of cases by unidentified manufacturers, and is arranged chronologically. The third subseries includes case covers by unidentified manufacturers, and is arranged chonologically. The fourth subseries consists of mats, and is arranged according to manufacturer, and chronologically under each manufacturer heading.
Series VI. Associated Printed Material, contains 52 items and spans the dates 1843-1899. It consists of Trade Cards for photographers in Connecticut, Massachusetts, Maine, New Hampshire, and Rhode Island; Advertising Materials, which includes a flier, a broadside, and a sign, each advertising different photographers; and Newspaper Advertisements, which include issues of The Boston Daily Bee and clippings of newspaper advertisements for daguerreotypists. Other printed material includes engravings based on daguerreotypes.
Appendix. Concordance of Numbers, consists of a listing of numbering schemes applied to the material by Peter Palmquist, and the corresponding number assigned by the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Portrait photography -- 19th century; California -- Biography -- Portraits; Great Britain -- Biography -- Portraits; United States -- Biography -- Portraits; Ambrotypes (photographs); Cased photographs; Cases (containers); Collodion processes; Daguerreotypes (photographs); Engravings (prints); Salted paper prints; Tintypes (prints); Studio portraits; Allen, Charles V., 1828-; Amy, George -- Portraits; Anderson, C. A., fl. 1859 -- Portraits; Atkinson, S. J.; Beals, Albert J.; Beardsley, B. C.; Broadbent, S. (Samuel), 1810-1881; Brown, C. D., fl. 1857 -- Portraits; Cammerer, Eugene -- Portraits; Carl, Edward -- Portraits; Cary, Charles H.; Clayton, James A. (James Atkins), 1831-1896; Cole, Cornelius, 1822-1924 -- Portraits; Cook, William H.; Coombs, F. (Frederick); Corning, Etta -- Portraits; Crocker, Charles, 1822-1888 -- Portraits; Cullen, James, Jr. -- Portraits; Dana, William Goodwin, 1797-1858 -- Portraits; Daniels, A. F. (Austin Fitzerland), 1832-; Drummond, Jane, fl. 1851 -- Portraits; Failing, F. M. -- Portraits; Fardon, G. R.; Fetter, Harvey G.; Fitzgibbon, John H., 1816?-1882; Ford, James May, 1827-approximately 1877; Fry, John D., 1819- -- Portraits; Garrison, Cornelius K. (Cornelius Kingsland), 1809-1885 -- Portraits; Gutekunst, Frederick, 1831-1917; Haight, Henry H., 1825-1878 -- Portraits; Hale, L.H., 1823-1885; Hamilton, Charles F., approximately 1825-; Hamilton, George D.; Harris, Theodore; Hartwell, Albert -- Portraits; Hathaway, William; Hawes, Charles E.; Heron, Matilda A., 1830-1877 -- Portraits; Hickling, J.; Higgins, Thomas J.; Hoffman, Ogden, 1822-1891 -- Portraits; Holladay, Ben, 1819-1887 -- Portraits; Jackson, Orin F. -- Portraits; Johnson, George Howard, 1823-; Kewen, E. J. C. (Edward John Cage), 1825-1879 -- Portraits; Lenox, Isaac Shaw; Lewis, Cordelia W. -- Portraits; Lid, A. S. -- Portraits; Livingston, Elizabeth Margaret -- Portraits; Long, Enoch; Lyman, Moses, 1768-1844 -- Portraits; Maxham, B. D. (Benjamin Dexter), 1821-1899; McIntyre, Sterling C.; Merriam, Jennie -- Portraits; Merrill, James O.; Merrill, Selah, 1837-1909 -- Portraits; Miller, Jack, fl. 1851 -- Portraits; Mills, Darius Ogden, 1825-1910 -- Portraits; Nancki, Fred -- Portraits; Norcross, Oliver H. P., 1824-1871; Outley, John J.; Palmquist, Peter E.; Phillips, J. A.; Pine, George W.; Plumbe, John, 1809-1857; Pratt, Carrie Campbell Crittenden -- Portraits; Ralston, Samuel W., 1832-1858 -- Portraits; Ralston, William Chapman, 1826-1875 -- Portraits; Ramsdell, Joseph -- Portraits; Rehn, Isaac; Ruth, J.; Selby, Thomas H., 1820-1875 -- Portraits; Selleck, Silas Wright, approximately 1828-1885; Sharon, William, 1821-1885 -- Portraits; Shaw, Seth Louis; Sherman, William T. (William Tecumseh), 1820-1891 -- Portraits; Shew, Jacob, approximately 1826-1879; Shew, Myron, 1824-1891; Shew, William J., 1820-1903; Shields, C. S., fl. 1859 -- Portraits; Showalter, Daniel -- Portraits; Silver, O. B.; Smith, Ben, fl. 1852 -- Portraits; Spooner, John Pitcher, 1845-1917; Uslar, Francis -- Portraits; Vance, Robert H., 1825-1876; Wagener, Francis Otto -- Portraits; Waldo, William, 1832-1911 -- Portraits; Ware, William K. -- Portraits; Whitehurst, Jesse Harrison, 1819-1875; Wightman, Gertrude -- Portraits; William, Waldo, 1832-1911; Winans, Joseph W., 1820-1887 -- Portraits; Wise, Joseph -- Portraits; Wise, May -- Portraits; Arvizu family -- Portraits; Perlata family; Vallejo family -- Portraits; Culver & Fellows (Newport, New Hampshire); Pine & Bells (Troy, New York); Shaw & Johnson (San Francisco, California); Spooner Brothers (Springfield, Massachusetts)
- Images by Identified Photographers, Series I; (161 items)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Images by Identified Photographers, is organized geographically into twelve subseries beginning with California, which represents the majority of identified photographers, followed by other states in alphabetical order, followed by Great Britain, and then by unknown locations. Name headings in each subseries are arranged alphabetically, and items under each name heading are arranged chronologically.
  - CALIFORNIA PHOTOGRAPHERS
    - Clayton, James Atkins (1831-1896)
      San Jose
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a girl standing between a seated female holding a handkerchief and a man, circa 1856-60 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Quarter-plate hand-tinted clear-glass ambrotype with metal back plate; original seal; evidence of asphaltum removal; stain in upper area of image
        Blindstamp on mat, "J. A. Clayton / San Jose"
        Full black leather case, with an elaborate geometric scroll motif with jewel motif in center of cover
        Behind image an erased pencil inscription, "Maryu" on green backing paper. Inscription on metal back plate, "this backing added 5-22-88 / K.A."
      - Ambrotype in a half case, of a girl and a woman, circa 1856-60 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; original seal; cover glass behind mat
        Blindstamp on mat, "J. A. Clayton / San Jose [California]"
      - Two ambrotypes in one case, one depicting a man and the other a woman, circa 1858 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted ruby-glass ambrotypes with asphaltum coating; original seals; cover glass behind mats
        Blindstamp on mats, "J. A. Clayton / San Jose [California]"
        Full brown thermoplastic case with Grape Cluster motif
    - Cook, William H.
      Marysville
      - Tintype with no case of a man posed sitting and mixing liquid, identified as an occupational self-portrait of photographer William Cook, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted tintype and mat
        Label affixed to back of plate, "Wm. H. Cook / Mixing Material to / use in Picture business in 1868"
    - Coombs, Frederick C. (1803-1874)
      San Francisco
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, 1850-52 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype; modern seal
        Blindstamp bottom center of mat, "F. COOMBS"
        Leather case with diamond motif in center
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man wearing a top hat with hand on vest, 1850-52 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype; partially sealed
        Leather case with single flower in oval medallion motif and varnished cover
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man identified as Orin F. Jackson, 1851 Dec (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Quarter-plate daguerreotype; original seal
        Full pigskin case with gold floral filigree
        Paper in the case, "San Francisco, CAL / Dec. 1850 / Orin F. Jackson / to Annie L Staigg / Feb. 20th 1851, Newport, R.I."
    - Fardon, George Robinson (1807-1886)
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a man and woman, identified as Joseph Wise and May Wise, circa 1857 (Box 54, Folder 8)
        Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype
      - Wet collodion process on leather, not in a case, of a man and woman identified as Joseph Wise and May Wise, circa 1857 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Sixth-plate wet collodion process on leather
        Inscription on verso, "Joseph & May Wise"
        Reverse image of Item 8
    - Ford, James May (1827-circa 1877)
      San Francisco or Sacramento
      - Daguerreotype in half a case, of a man, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype, modern seal
        Blindstamp bottom on mat, "M. FORD"
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, circa 1852-54 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype; broken seal
        Full leather case with scroll and leaf motif, imprint on velvet, "FORD'S / DAGUERREAN GALLERY / CLAY ST. / SAN FRANCISCO / AND / J ST. SACRAMENTO CITY"
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a boy and a man, circa 1853-54 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        Quarter-plate daguerreotype; partial seal
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1854 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype
        Blindstamp on bottom of mat, "J. M. FORD"
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, identified as actress Matilda A. Heron, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        Quarter-plate daguerreotype
        Full leather case
    - Hamilton, Charles F. (b. circa 1825)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1854 (Box 2, Folder 15)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype; sealed
        Blindstamp on mat, "HAMILTON"
        Full brown leather case with the "Maiden with Cornucopia" motif (Rinhart #163)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a woman holding a small purse, circa 1854-56 (Box 2, Folder 16)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype; partial seal
        Blindstamp on mat, "HAMILTON, SAN FRANCISCO"
        Full brown leather case with mixed floral motif.
      - Ambrotype in a case, of an elderly man, circa 1854-56 (Box 2, Folder 17)
        Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum/varnish backing and black photographic paper backing; original seal
        Full brown leather case with floral bouquet motif
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman, circa 1854-60 (Box 2, Folder 18)
        Sixth-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum/varnish backing with black velvet; blackened photo paper inserted between plate and velvet; no seal
        Full brown papier-mache case with cross-hatched medallion center with floral scroll motif
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1854-69 (Box 2, Folder 19)
        Quarter-plate hand-tinted clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; original seal
        Full brown leather case with floral scroll motif
        Inscription on paper backing, "case not original to image"
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman wearing a fur wrap, circa 1854-69 (Box 2, Folder 20)
        Quarter-plate hand-tinted ambrotype with leather backing; original seal with leather
        Full leather case with geometric floral scroll motif
    - Higgins, Thomas J.
      Sacramento
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, identified as brick mason holding a trowel, circa 1859 (Box 3, Folder 21)
        Half-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype
        Full brown leather case with floral arrangement in a vase motif
    - Johnson, George Howard, (b. circa 1823)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, 1849-52 (Box 3, Folder 22)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype; no seal
        Blindstamp lower right on mat, "G. H. JOHNSON"
        Full leather case with Curved Diamond motif (Rinhart #199)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, 1849-52 (Box 3, Folder 23)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted daguerreotype; original seal
        Full brown leather case with floral bouquet motif. Imprint on velvet case pad, "GEO. H. JOHNSON / ARTIST / SACRAMENTO"
        Full brown leather case with "A Spray of Roses" motif (Rinhart #131)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, 1849-52 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a man, identified as possibly Frank or Father Burlingham, 1849-52 (Box 3, Folder 25)
        Label affixed to cover glass has inscription, "Fr. Burlingham"
    - Norcross, Oliver H. P., (1824-1871)
      Weaverville
      - Daguerreotype in a case, of a postmortem boy, identified as James Cullen, Jr., circa 1856 (Box 3, Folder 26)
        Sixth-plate daguerreotype; modern seal
        Full leather case with single flower medallion motif
        Inscription on paper lining behind plate, "James Cullen, Jr./ Weaverville, CA / c. 1856"
    - Ruth, J.
      - Ambrotype not in a case, of a girl and boy, circa 1855-59 (Box 3, Folder 27)
        Quarter-plate ambrotype; modern seal
        Identity of photographer based on its acquisition with a business card
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1855-59 (Box 3, Folder 28)
        Ninth-plate clear-glass ambrotype
        Full brown leather case with eight scroll rosette motif; Imprint on velvet pad of case, "J. RUTH'S GALLERY / D. St. near THIRD / MARYSVILLE, CAL."
      - Ambrotype in a period frame, of two women and a man, circa 1855-59 (Box 43, Folder 29)
        Quarter-plate clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum and fabric backing.
        Period wall-frame with gold paint over entire frame; attached card: "J. RUTH, / DAGUERREAN, AMBROTYPIST, / AND / PHOTOGRAPHER, / D. Street, Opposite the Haun House, / MARYSVILLE, CAL. / MR. RUTH has the best arranged light in the State. Daguerreotypes, / Ambrotypes, and Photographs, taken in all kinds of weather, and WAR- / RANTED AS GOOD AS THE BEST. Prices as low as at any other first-class / gallery"
    - Selleck, Silas Wright (circa 1828-1885)
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a woman and a boy in a dress, circa 1856-60 (Box 3, Folder 30)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted ruby-glass ambrotype; original seal
        Blindstamp lower left on mat, "Silas Selleck / San / Francisco"
        Full brown leather case with three-flower bouquet in center and simple leaf scrolling
      - Ambrotype in a case, of a man, circa 1856-60 (Box 4, Folder 31)
        Sixth-plate hand-tinted clear-glass ambrotype with asphaltum backing; no seal